Guide to the Harry C. Peterson Papers, ca. 1880-1944
Department of Special Collections
Peterson, Harry C. Papers,
ca. 1880-1944
M0649
Peterson, Harry C.
2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The collection contains correspondence, notes, memorabilia, typescripts. Included is material pertaining to Stanford University and Sutters Fort.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1993.
Biography
Harry Claude Peterson never met a historical fact or artifact that he didn't like. The inveterate historian spent his entire adult life in one position after another related to history, particularly California Gold Rush Days.
Harry was born in Algona, Iowa, in 1876, son of Julius E. Peterson, a Norwegian mechanician. Leland Stanford had learned of the elder Peterson in Europe and brought him to Stanford University to teach Machine Shop Practices. Young Harry was educated in public schools in Algona and Palo Alto, California. He was in the photographic business in Palo Alto for a time. He was married in 1902 and had one son, Austin Peterson.
Harry was named Director and Curator of the Stanford University Museum of Fine Arts (now the Cantor Center) in 1899, where he remained until 1918, adding collections to the Museum and writing historical papers. He also acquired his own collection of historical books and documents while serving as Curator. During his residence in Palo Alto, he served on the city counsel for eight years.
Harry's next endeavor was as head of Field Research for the California History Department of the California State Library. He remained in that position for three years, and then joined the Oakland Tribune as feature writer of California history for the paper, for another three years. In 1925, he was named Curator of Sutter's Fort Museum in Sacramento, California, and became a charter member of the American Association of Museums.
Harry Peterson's credits are many, from over three hundred published stories and speeches and countless photographs concerning California History, many for professional and trade publications and meetings. He was responsible for energizing the public to the historical value of Sutter's Fort. He served on the Southern Pacific Railroad Company's selection committee to identify historical sites along its lines. He also acted as historical consultant on several Hollywood films of the Gold Rush days, such as The Pony Express, The Big Trail, the Fighting Caravan, and Sutter's Gold.. He was a member of the Board of Directors of the Sacramento Golden Empire Centennial in 1939. His energy, exemplified by his many activities, appeared to be unstoppable, but Harry Peterson died suddenly of a heart attack, in his office at Sutter's Fort, in 1941. His series of articles on the Gold Rush for the Oakland Tribune were collected in book form, The 49er, published posthumously by the Doubleday Company in 1949.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Correspondence, notes, memorabilia, typescripts. Included is material pertaining to Stanford University and Sutters Fort.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Berner, Bertha.; Couper, William.; Covey, F.W.; Davis, Horace.; Gross, H.H.; Hewes, Anna Lathrop.; Holzman, R.O.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; Lathrop, Charles G. (Charles Gardner), 1849-1914.; Nash, H.C.; Schmid, Rupert.; Spencer, Francis.; Stanford, Jane Lathrop, 1828-1905.; Wilbur, Ray Lyman, 1875-1949.; Stanford University--History.; Sutters' Fort.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Peterson Family Material
  - Harry Claude Peterson biography and resumes n.d., (4 sheets) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See also B 3 (OS), Fs 1,4, and 5.
  - Personal Correspondence1907-1937, (11 letters & 4 postcards) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence to H. C. Peterson, from Arthur S. Dudley family1909-1937, (3 items) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Stock certificate (gold mine), agreement to purchase (blank) 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Commemorative silk ribbons1889-1916, (14 items) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photo album, Austin Petersonn.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellany (Golden Gate Bridge ticket, H. C. Peterson business card, receipt 1932-1937, (3 items). (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series 2. Material Relating to Stanford University and Stanford Museum
  - "Founding of Stanford University (1891)"1931, (1 pamphlet). (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Stanford University Opening Day Exercises" 1891, (1 pamphlet). (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stanford Circulars 1 & 2 (with personal card of Mrs. Leland [Jane] Stanford). 1891 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Stanford University student testimonials, King-Richardson, Company 1899, (1 pamphlet). (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Stanford University Commencement 1901, (1 program). (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Address to Stanford University Trustees," Jane L. Stanford 1899, (1 pamphlet). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Address to Stanford University Trustees," Jane L. Stanford 1903, (1 pamphlet). See also B 3, F 3. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter to Jane L. Stanford, from F. W. Covey (Palo Alto Stock Farm), September 1, 1893, (2 sheets). (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter to Jane L. Stanford, from H. H. Gross,July 21, 1893, (2 sheets). (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Letters to Jane L. Stanford, from Francis Spencer (Stanford Trustee), C. F. Crocker, C. S. Lathrop, C. P. Huntington.August 17, 1890 and August 17, 1893, (2 letters). (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letters to Jane L. Stanford, from Horace Davis (Stanford Trustee), July 13 and July 19, 1904, (2 letters). (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Letters to H. C. Nash (secretary to Leland W. Stanford), from R. O. Holzman, July 17, July 20, and August 5, 1893, (3 letters). (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Letter to H. C. Nash, from H. H. Gross, July 21, 1893, ( 1 sheet). (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letter to H. C. Nash, from Rupert Schmid,August 2, 1893, (1 sheet) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - In Memoriam: Leland Stanford, Jr., book with letter attached to Mrs. Jane L. Stanford, from William Couper. 1885 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Memorial Address: Leland Stanford," U. S. Senate, Washington D. C., 1893, (1 pamphlet). (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "In Memoriam: Anna Lathrop Hewes,"August 2, 1892, (1 pamphlet). (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Leland Stanford Junior Museum," Stanford University Press, 1903, ( 1 pamphlet). (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Timothy Hopkins, Charles G. Lathrop, Anna Lathrop Hewes, David Starr Jordan, F. W. Covey, Palo Alto Stock Farm.
  - Letter to H. C. Peterson, Curator, Leland Stanford, Jr. Museum, from Bertha Berner (Secretary to Jane L. Stanford), August 19, 1903, (1 sheet). (Box 1, Folder 26)
    See also B 3, F 1.
  - Letters to H. C. Peterson, from Charles G. Lathrop, July 6, 1901, and Mrs. Charles G. Lathrop, December 28, 1903, (2 letters). (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Letter to H. C. Peterson, from David [Starr] Jordan, November 14, 1902, (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 28)
    See also B 3, F 5.
  - Letter to H. C. Peterson, from R. [Ray] L. [Lyman] Wilbur, September 29, 1916, (1 sheet). (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Letter from H. C. Peterson to [Mr. Bube?], with invoice, October 14, 1907, (2 sheets) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Additional Stanford Museum correspondence to H. C. Peterson 1901-1917, (8 letters, 1 postcard) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Envelopes to H. C. Peterson 1910-1916, (5 envelopes) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - News clipping, "New Library at Stanford Has Browsing Room." [ July 26 1919?]. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Timothy Hopkins.
  - Photo, note, and envelope re Herbert Hoover[1912], (3 items). (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Letter to Stanford student's parents, from Herbert Hoover, October 5, 1942, (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Palo Stock Farm Catalog," auction, November 26, 1897, (1 pamphlet). (Box 1, Folder 36)
    See also B 1, F 15.
  - Photographs of early Stanford University [1900], (16 B/W photos and colored postcards). (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Souvenir ticket to Stanford house, Michigan Bluff, Placer County, California, June 2, 1928, (1 item.) (Box 1, Folder 38)
    See also B 4, F 1.
  - "Scientific Physiognomist." Fragment, signed by Mary Olmstead Stanton. n.d., (1 sheet). (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Blank invoices,Vina Distillery 1890?, (10 items) (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Series 3. Material Relating to Fort Sutter and the Discovery of Gold
  - Photographs of Sutter's Fort (n.d.) and H. C. Peterson, Curator (1932)., (4 items) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - " Sutter's Fort Historical Museum," pamphlet[1944?], (48 pages). (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "The Discovery of Gold in California," pamphlet1919, (4 pages). (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters by P. B .Beakart, stating that first gold found in 1848 was not nugget-sized 1921, 1931, (2 letters) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "California Pioneers," speech, John C. Chambers,February 22, 1918, (9 pages). (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Sutter's Fort Historical Museum," typescript, by H. C. Peterson 1925, ( 5 sheets). (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Hock Farm," partial typescript, by H. C. Peterson n.d., (3 sheets). (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "It Never Occurred To Me," typescript, by H.C. Peterson n.d., (2 sheets). (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sutter's Fort Museum Collection, partial typescript, [by H. C. Peterson?] n.d., (2 sheets). (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Benicia," typescript, H. C. Peterson, September 12, 1927, (8 sheets). (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Marysville," partial typescript, by H.C. Peterson, September 14,1935, (4 sheets ). (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, California State Historical Association, Sutter's Fort, H. C. Peterson, Acting Secretary,November 26, 1934, (3 sheets) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Lists of Fort Sutter display labels n.d., (5 sheets). (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Sutter's Fort Museum correspondence, to H. C. Peterson, 1920-1929, (11 letters, 2 postcards) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sutter's Fort Museum correspondence, to H. C. Peterson, 1930-1940, (16 letters, 4 postcards) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence to/from B. F. Hall and H. C. Peterson 1930-1937, (3 letters and 1 postcard) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence from H.C Peterson 1927-1936, (4 letters). (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letter from Karen Kearns (Huntington Library) to Gerald Lucero regarding authenticity of attached letter, purportedly written by John A. Sutter, May 17, 1988, (2 sheets). (Box 2, Folder 18)
    See also B 3, F 9.
  - Photograph, John A. Sutter.n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Copy of will, Anna Sutter, dated 1881 1926, (4 sheets). (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Invitation to H. C. Peterson to visit branches of the Sutter Family, from M. Van Volbeck,January 18, 1928. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letters from Paulita de Sutter to H.C. Peterson,1938, (4 letters). (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Photographs, John Bidwell n.d., (3 photos) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Letter to John Bidwell, from Mrs. T. Lynch Mineral Point, November 13, 1851, (1 letter). (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letter to H.C. Peterson, from Charles E. Bancroft, regarding Bidwell's BarMarch 19, 1925, (1 sheet) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Letters from Charles H.Davis regarding disposition of effects, May 1, 1928, (2 letters). (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Letters from/to A. William Lund and H. C. Peterson, May 19 and 26, 1928, (2 letters). (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Letter to H. C Peterson from E. Brown regarding C. H. Davis, July 9, 1928, (1 letter) (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Letter to H. C. Peterson from Capt. W.R. Scott regarding C. H. Davis, July 18, 1928, (1 sheet). (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Typescript and handwritten draft regarding C. H. Davis n.d., (2 sheets). (Box 2, Folder 30)
    See also Box 3, F 10.
  - Correspondence between H. C. Peterson and the Progressive Magazine, January 27 to February 14, 1928, (7 letters). (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - The Progressive Magazine facsimile and book advertisement. n.d., (2 items). (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence between Julius Loeb and H. C. Peterson regarding the Pony Express,August 4 and 25,1927, and February 20, 1928, (4 letters). (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - List of Candidates [for California Historical Society ?]. prepared by H. C. Peterson. n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Program, Garden Fete, for delegates to Pan American Reciprocal Trade Conference, August 28, 1930. Replica: California Republic flag, (2 items). (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Illustrated card and poem, from E. A. Burbank (8x10 inches) to H. C. Peterson (and envelope)August 23, 1938. (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Photographs commemorating "Days of the 49ers"[1939], (8 photographs). (Box 2, Folder 37)
    See also B 3, F2.
  - Photograph (8x10 inches), Morgan Wallace as General John Fremont in film Sutter's Gold. n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Luggage tag, H. C. Peterson, Sutter's Hotel, San Francisco, California. n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence to H. C. Peterson regarding Whiskerinos Club, 1920s, (2 letters, 3 postcards) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous envelopes1928-1937 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence to H. C. Peterson regarding early California history 1928, 1938, (5 letters) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - "Romance of California," [text by H. C. Peterson ?], Sacramento Chamber of Commerce (pamphlet, [1927], 22 pages). (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - "Romance of California," text by H. C. Peterson, Sacramento Chamber of Commerce (pamphlet, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    47 pages, with map).
  - Crofutt's New Overland Tourist, and Pacific Coast Guide (partial copy). [1880] (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Historical notes on crossing the plains by H. C. Peterson n.d., (8 notes). (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - "Captain Jean J Voiget," typescripts, [by H. C. Peterson ?] n.d., (two copies, 8 pages). (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Notebook, compiled by H. C. Peterson, relating to J.J. Voiget's first survey of Yerba Buena (San Francisco) in 1839-40. 1904 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    (Notes from several historical sources, photos of dispositions of early settlers, maps, news clippings).
  - Photograph of painting of Yerba Buena, [ by John J. Voiget. n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Land grant testimony of John J. Voiget and Wm. I. Richardson, schedule of testimony, plot plan, San Francisco, 1848. 1848, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Letter to H. C. Peterson from Alice Jeanette Voigetn.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Letter to Raphael Weill, from H. C. Peterson regarding Yerba Buena Cove, March 31, 1920, (1 letter) (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Photograph, U.S. Mint [San Francisco ?].1904 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - "The Highway of Romance" (Mother Lode State Highway), n.d., (pamphlet, 8 pages). (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Program, Dedication of Fremont Tablet, Buttes, California, April 15, 1923. (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - News clipping on John C. Fremont, New York Tribune, June 20, 1856. (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Chinese Camp (California), typescript by H. C. Peterson n.d., (11 pages). (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Chinese Camp (California), handwritten notes [by H.C. Peterson?] n.d., (4 sheets). (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Coloma (California), handwritten notes [by H. C. Peterson?] n.d., (4 sheets). (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Coyote Diggings (California), handwritten notes, [by H. C. Peterson], n.d., (3 notes, 1 envelope). (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Volcano (California), handwritten notes, [ by H. C. Peterson ?] n.d., (1 sheet). (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Announcement, State Mining Celebration, Mariposa, California, June 20-21,1 931, (1 sheet). (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - California history, handwritten notes, [H. C. Peterson ?] n.d., (2 sheets) (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - California pioneer tombstones (8 photographs).n.d. (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Gold mining towns n.d., ( 8 photographs, and 1 chit from gold mining company). (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Letter from John B. Montgomery to E. L. Norton, from Boston August 7, 1862, (1 sheet) (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Monterey-Carmel (California), n.d, ( 8 photographs). (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Letter to H. C. Peterson about San Mateo California from C. P Cooley, Palo Alto, California, January 1, 1928, (1 letter). (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Photograph taken at Mission San Jose, California,[ with H. C. Peterson?] n.d. (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Handwritten notes on "A Threatened Offense." California Penal Code). n.d. (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - "Central Pacific Railroad," pamphlet 1913, (2 copies). (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Sun Valley, Idaho, typescript [by H. C. Peterson ?].1938 (Box 2, Folder 72)
- Series 4. Oversize materials
  - News clipping, "Mrs. Stanford Dies in Sudden Agony at a Honolulu Hotel, Declaring,'I am poisoned!'." San Francisco Chronicle, March 2, 1905. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - News clipping, announcing 1849 centennial, Sacramento Union, March 22, 1936. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Policy statement to Jane L. Stanford from Stanford University Trustees, June 5, 1903., See also B 1 F 14. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Stanford University map.n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Partial letter [to Jane L. Stanford ?] from Jesse Knight Jordan n.d., (3 pages). (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Resources of California, [ about Stanford University], September 1886. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - News clipping. "The Dizzy Cycle that John A Sutter Executed in His Lifetime," by H. C. Peterson, Oakland Tribune, March 30, 1924. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Life at Sutter's Fort," play script, with accompanying letter by Irene Clark to H. C. PetersonMarch 2, 1936, (script 21 pages, letter 2 pages). (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letter by John A. Sutter [purported] to Ernesto Hopkins n.d., (1 letter). (Box 3, Folder 9)
    See also B 1 F 18
  - Letter, partial, [by H.C. Peterson] regarding Captain C. H. Davis n.d., (11 sheet). (Box 3, Folder 10)
    See also B 2, F 31
  - Chattel mortgage agreement: Ralph Joines to Harry C. Peterson, regarding tools, Sutter's Fort. 1939 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Boyd and Barber in San Francisco in mid-1800s, typescript n.d., (4 sheets). (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - California Indians, partial typescriptn.d. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - News clippings. Marysville Advertiser, 1854 and 1857, (13 clippings). (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Handwritten copy of Sonoma (California) County law, 1857, (1 sheet). (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Statement of charges incurred by patients of St. Luke's Hospital, San Francisco, September 1 to September 30, 1876., (2 sheets) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Accounts record [in Spanish]. 1851, (14 pages) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Proclamation [in Portugese], signed by Joaquin O. Alvarez and Jose de O Barbazo, April 26, 1826., (2 sheets). (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Statement from Mutuo Soccorso della Compagna Carabiniere Swizzeri [in Italian], San Francisco,December 1, 1888. (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Series 5. Photoprints
  - Photoprints of Leland Stanford house at Michigan Bluff, California n.d., (8 glass negatives). (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photoprint of Peter Slater's Saloon, Fort Sutter, (H.C. Peterson behind bar), n.d., (1 glass negative, cracked) (Box 4, Folder 2)